<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="nnan0126" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
   <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b">
      <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-nnan">nnan0126</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Gutzon Borglum photographs and other material, 1901-1920</titleproper>
            <author>David Hill</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <date>© 2013</date>
            <address>
               <addressline>American Numismatic Society Archives</addressline>
               <addressline>75 Varick Street, 11th floor</addressline>
               <addressline>New York, NY 10013</addressline>
            </address>
            <publisher>ANS Archives</publisher>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Finding aid encoded by David Hill using EADitor ©2013</creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in English</langusage>
      </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <unittitle>Gutzon Borglum photographs and other material</unittitle>
         <abstract>Signed photographs and other items from Gutzon Borglum.</abstract>
         <physloc audience="internal">ANS Vault</physloc>
         <physdesc>
            <extent>0.2 cubic feet (1 box)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <langmaterial>
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
         <unitdate normal="1901/1920">1901-1920</unitdate>
         <repository>American Numismatic Society</repository>
         <daogrp>
            <daodesc>
               <p>Gutzon Borglum working on the statue of General Philip Sheridan for Sheridan Circle, Washington, D.C., ca. 1908</p>
            </daodesc>
         </daogrp>
      </did>
      <processinfo audience="internal">
         <head>Processing Information</head>
         <p>Rodin portrait and letter removed from water damaged frame in January 2013, but are both still attached to matte. Two of the photographs of the Sheriden statue are water damaged, including the one of Borglum with the “single casting” of the horse, but most of the image areas in both are untouched.</p>
      </processinfo>
      <controlaccess>
         <persname authfilenumber="867200" source="viaf">Borglum, Gutzon, 1867-1941</persname>
         <persname authfilenumber="36923874" source="viaf">Rodin, Auguste, 1840-1917</persname>
         <genreform authfilenumber="300046300" source="aat">Photographs</genreform>
         <genreform authfilenumber="300026877" source="aat">Correspondence</genreform>
         <genreform authfilenumber="300215389" source="aat">Magazines (Periodicals)</genreform>
         <subject source="lcsh" authfilenumber="sh85119000">Sculptors</subject>
         <subject source="lcsh" authfilenumber="sh85082802">Medalists</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <scopecontent>
         <p>Contains a halftone reproduction of a sketched portrait signed in ink by Borglum, with the words “To you Archer M. Huntington”; a copy of The Delineator (v.95 n.6, December 1919) with the article “Paderewski’s Renunciation,” featuring one of Borglum’s drawings, signed in ink; five signed photographs of his statue of General Philip Sheridan for Sheridan Circle, Washington, D.C., two of which show work being done in the studio and another showing Borglum with the horse piece (noted as “single casting”), inscribed to Huntington; four signed photographs of unidentified busts, one with the year 1920 and one with 1919; a signed photograph of what is labeled on the reverse as “I Piped for You and You Would not Dance,” which shows a split where a reclining male figure has been cut from the standing female figure, copyright 1905; a halftone reproduction of a sketched portrait of August Rodin by Borglum dated July 3, 1901, and a letter from Rodin to an artist (illegible) regarding a meeting in Paris to discuss having a portrait made, both mounted together in a matte where they had at one time been displayed in a frame.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical Note</head>
         <p>Sculptor John Gutzon de la Mothe Borglum (1867-1941) designed the American Numismatic Society’s Membership Medal in 1910. Born near Bear Lake, Idaho, to Danish parents, he lived in Utah, Nebraska, Kansas, and California as a youth. As an adult he opened a small studio and earned some commissions, eventually traveling to Paris where he studied at the École des Beaux-Arts and formed friendships with such notable artists as the sculptor Auguste Rodin. Having returned in 1901 to work in the United States, he continued to find success. His Mares of Diomedes, for example, was the first sculpture by an American to be purchased by the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City, and his marble bust of Abraham Lincoln has been on display at the U.S. Capitol since 1911. His most famous work is no doubt the four U.S. presidents carved into Mount Rushmore in the Black Hills of South Dakota.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <acqinfo audience="internal">
         <head>Provenance</head>
         <p>Provenance is uncertain, but several of the items are inscribed to Archer M. Huntington.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accessrestrict>
         <head>Access</head>
         <p>Collection open to all researchers.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <custodhist audience="internal">
         <head>Custodial History</head>
         <p>Transferred from Curatorial to Archives on February 8, 2010. No prior custodial history on file.</p>
      </custodhist>
      <prefercite>
         <head>Preferred Citation</head>
         <p>Gutzon Borglum photographs and other material, 1901-1920, Archives, American Numismatic Society</p>
      </prefercite>
      <userestrict>
         <head>Restrictions</head>
         <p>Copyright restrictions may apply. Permission to publish or reproduce must be secured from the American Numismatic Society.</p>
      </userestrict>
   </archdesc>
</ead>